<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unlimited God, not limited by any of the children of light, but by them who are in the darkness and straitness, such would be limiting the unlimited God from the Spirit of the Lord is this given forth, that all such may read with the eye which is not busie, nor looks into things above its reach : from one who becomes all to all, to gain some to Christ ... : also, a warning, and a charge from the Lord God, to all the Baptists teachers every where ... : also, a true discovery of the way to the kingdome within ... / given forth from the Spirit of the Lord, in Humphry Wollrich ...</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39138</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18218911</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18218911</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107206</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107206)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1138:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unlimited God, not limited by any of the children of light, but by them who are in the darkness and straitness, such would be limiting the unlimited God from the Spirit of the Lord is this given forth, that all such may read with the eye which is not busie, nor looks into things above its reach : from one who becomes all to all, to gain some to Christ ... : also, a warning, and a charge from the Lord God, to all the Baptists teachers every where ... : also, a true discovery of the way to the kingdome within ... / given forth from the Spirit of the Lord, in Humphry Wollrich ...</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped and stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107206:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE UNLIMITED GOD, Not limited by any of the CHILDREN of LIGHT, BUT BY Them who are in the Darkneſs and Strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſuch would be limiting the Unlimited God. From the Spirit of the Lord is this given forth, that all ſuch may Read with the Eye which is not buſie, nor looks into things above its Reach. From one who becomes All to All, to gain ſome to Chriſt, and hath true Freedom in the Lord to go into the Water, that I may bring to the Rock, and ſave one out of the Sea, which is ready to be Drowned, and Loſt. Alſo, A warning, and a Charge from the Lord God, to all the Baptiſts Teachers every where, who are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit, to ceaſe Teaching, or Deceiving any longer. Alſo, A true diſcovery of the way to the Kingdome Within, from all the Prieſts, and Falſe Teachers, who are crying, Loe here, and loe there without, In the way of <hi>Balaam</hi> for Filthy lucre ſake, <hi>Mathew</hi> 24. which Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, and <hi>John</hi> ſaid was come, and the World went out after them, who went out from the Light ſixteen Hundred years agoe. Given forth from the SPIRIT of the LORD, in <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHRY WOLLRICH,</hi> who was not ſent to Baptiſe, But to preach the Goſpel; yet hath Baptiſed one with Water for the Goſpels ſake; and am not without a Law to God, yet am made All things to All, to gain ſome to Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 78.41.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They turned back and tempted God, and limited the Holy One of Iſrael.</p>
            </q>
            <q>Such have the Form, but not the Power: but yet would Limit.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:107206:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107206:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THe Brother-hood is in Chriſt, which is not Divided, out of all Diviſion, Judging, &amp;c cenſuring one another, are all that are in him, to whom all Judgement is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. To you all, this is the word of the Lord God, and a Charge from my Father to you all, Judge nothing before the Time, as all do, which Judge with that which is for Judgement; who have got the Forme, but are out of the Spirit, and Spirituall Man, which Judgeth all things: and though I am but as yeſterday in compariſon of many, who were in Chriſt before me, yet I care not for mans Judgement; neither do I judge my own ſelf for that thing for which I am Judged: but all you my Friends, be ſober, and cool in your mindes, and wait in that which is the Everlaſting Day, and makes all things manifeſt, and will not be limited by any, who are in the Darkneſſe, nor Judged; but will Judge, and Condemne all who would Judge him, and limit him, as he in all Ages hath done: and he is now the ſame, and all that have a forme, but would limit the power, ſhall know it in Gods time; and this is laid upon me from the Lord God Almighty, to warne all ſuch that they be ſilent, and ſtop their mouthes before him, whoſe ways is unſearchable, and will not be limited now, but is unlimited, as in all Ages he was: and becauſe I have true freedome in the Lord, and am not without a law to God herein, which is to Baptiſe one with water, though I was not ſent to Baptiſe, but to Preach the Goſpel, as <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to Baptiſe, but did Baptiſe (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.) by Permiſſion, and not by Commiſſion, that he might gain ſome unto Chriſt, who is the End of all Types, Shaddowes, and Figures, and the Everlaſting day into which <hi>Paul</hi> was come, where ſhaddowes flee away, who became all things to all, read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19. for though I be free from all men, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> I have made my ſelf ſervant unto all, that I might gain the more. And unto the <hi>Jewes</hi> I became as a <hi>Jew.</hi> (Mark) as a <hi>Jew,</hi> that I might gain the <hi>Jewes</hi> to them that are under the Law, as under the Law. Conſider where <hi>Paul</hi> was, whether he were not in Chriſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107206:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the end of the law, to them that were without law, as without law, being not without a law to God, but to the weak, he became as weak: (Mark) <hi>Paul</hi> the Aged, and chiefeſt of the Apoſtles, I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means ſave ſome: and this I do for the Goſpels ſake, as he did, that I might be partaker thereof with Joy.</p>
            <p>And though I have born an open Teſtimony for the Lord God, againſt all them who have been Baptiſed with Water, &amp; knew no better a leader &amp; guider thereinto than the Letter. The ſons of God, and ſervants of God, who were led into it, or ſhall be led into it by the Spirit of the Lord, which ſpirit will not be limited, I never did, nor never ſhall condemne any ſuch as this Woman, having given her teſtimony in publick, both before and ſince I Baptiſed her with Water, that ſhe was led by this Unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Spirit, and not from the Baptiſts rule and leader, which is the Letter, and kills, but by the Spirit, the Sons leader; and gives life, and the Children of the light wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this her teſtimony to be true: And likewiſe ſhe hath declared that, ſhe was moved of the Lord to deſire me only to Baptiſe her with Water, and ſaid, The ſpirit by which the Baptiſts are led, did not convince her, nor bring her to the knowledge of the Truth: And the Baptiſt Teacher, who would have had her to receive it of, ſome of them ſaid he, did believe ſhe was led to it by the Spirit of the Lord; yet neither he, nor his ſpirit did ſhe own; and this I leave upon all who fear the Lord, both ſmall and great to Judge, whether it is better to ſave life, or to deſtroy?</p>
            <p>And I have the Teſtimony of the Lord in me, that this is not againſt the Truth; neither ſhall it be a juſt occaſion of ſtumbling to any, who are really therein, but to ſuch as are in the Dark, and are looking, and judging with the Evil Eye, and have been Diſobedient to the Word in their own particulars: to ſuch this may be a ſtumbling ſtone; but all whoſe mindes are without, ſeeking a proof of Chriſt in me; to you, I ſay, Judge your ſelves, turn in,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107206:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and examine your ſelves; know you not that Chriſt is in ye, except ye be Reprobates. Receive the word as the <hi>Bereans</hi> did, and then ſearch the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. <hi>Paul,</hi> who denied Circumciſion, which was outward in the Fleſh, circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> that he might gain the Jewes, whoſe mindes were without, and bring them to the one Circumciſion, and one Baptiſme in ſpirit, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God. Read <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21, to the 25. where you may read, that Holy <hi>Paul</hi> ſhaved his Head, that he might take away the vail which was over the Jewes, and thereby bring them to their true Head, Chriſt, the end of the Law, and the end of all Vowes and Oathes, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.18. and ſo that none that feares the Lord may ſtumble hereat, be ye of what Sect or Forme ſoever, be ye faithfull to what ye know. I am you Brother, and Warne you all, and exhort you all: Come down into the cool, and low ſpirit, for you and I muſt ſtand or fall unto the Lord, our own Maſter: and this is ſafe for us all, and we ſhall be preſerved from that which cauſeth War, Striving, and falling out by the way. And oh, how do I deſire, and the Lord Gods knowes, to me it is a Joyfull thing, to ſee Brethren live together in Unity, not Biting, and Devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another; not ſtriving, and contending about thoſe things which <hi>Paul</hi> could do, or leave undone, as he ſaw occaſion miniſtred unto him by them, whom he had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to catch by guile; all minde your own as I doe herein, for that which goes out, and leads you out, will devour and deſile you; but if you are ſtaid at home, ye ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the ſpoile with him that deſtroyes that which defiles you: Prepare to meet the Lord, ye ſonnes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> whom the Lord hath choſen for his Peculiar Treaſure, and none ſay in your hearts, is not Chriſt the end of all theſe things which are outward? I ſay, he is to all that are in him, and ſinne not: But all are not come to this, who are convinced of the Truth, and where it is. And though they have heard the Lord calling them out of Aegypt, yet there is a Baptiſme in the Sea, and in the Cloud, and a great War, and mighty Enemies before they come to their Reſt, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107206:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>their deſired Heaven: and though the Light hath ſhined out of darkneſſe, and there be ſome ſeparation, and a firſt dayes work done, yet is not the new Creation wholly finiſhed, nor the Reſt wholly known, nor fully entred into, which remaines to the people of God. For he that is ſet down in the Reſt, in the Heavenly place in Chriſt Jeſus, is ceaſed from his own workes, as God did from his: and though the Lord hath rained down his Manna round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your Tents, yet the Clouds may return after the rain, and while the Figure, the Vaile, and the Cloud is ſtanding; and the firſt Tabernacle, wherein you have long pitched the way into the Holieſt of all, is not wholly known; ſo while you are Judging, or condemning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that which is for Judgement is ſtanding within, and he who is the firſt and the laſt, the beginning and the end of all ſhadowes, Types and figures, is yet not dwelt in, nor ſet down in by you, but lieth hid within the vaile, which vaile is done away in Chriſt, where circumciſion, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion availeth not any thing, but Faith that works by love: And we are all the Sons of God by Faith. Read <hi>Galathians</hi> 3.23. But before Faith came, we were kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, ſhut up unto the Faith which ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be revealed. Come down into the Deep you that have an Ear to hear, or a Heart to underſtand this, the Law is added becauſe of Sinne, and is the School-maſter to bring to Chriſt, who is the end both of Sinne and the Law, to which it was added: Read, and conſider <hi>Verſe</hi> 25. But after that Faith is come, we are no longer under a School-maſter, but we are all the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus: And as many of you, (Mark you Baptiſts) as many of you as have been Baptiſed into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt the end of all, and the body of dayes, times, and ſhaddowes. But this is not come to you, though you have been Baptiſed with Water; for your time is not in the Fathers hand, but your tongues is your own, and your time is alwayes, though Chriſts time, and the Fathers time ye know not; and therein ye can pray when ye will, and in your own will, which is contrary to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107206:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>God; ye can ſpeak evil of thoſe things ye know not, and ye exerciſe your ſelves in things that are too high for you. Therefore, to you all, this is the Word of the Lord God: All you Baptiſt Teachers, feed not the people with windy Doctrine, or words without the life: And I charge you all in the preſence of the Lord God, which confeſſe you have never heard his Voice at any time, but ſayes that God ſpeak not ſince the days of the Apoſtles. Ceaſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any longer, for his ſheep hear his voice, and his voice is the ſame now, that it was unto <hi>Adam, Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> not carnal, but ſpiritual; neither was it ever heard with any carnal Ear, nor his ſhape ſeen with any carnal Eye, but ye, by your own confeſſions, are Miniſters of the letter: Therefore I charge you all, that I may be clear of your bloud, leave murdering, for that Kils; but ſpeak, if the Spirit give you utterance, for that giveth life, and bringeth the Soul out of Death to hear its Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds Voice. And do not ſay we deny the Scriptures, or any of the Ordinances of God any more, as ye have often done, untill you hear us deny them, which we ſhall never do: but we owneth the Bible of the Scriptures to be a true Declaration of God, and Chriſt: but I ſay, all that own the Scriptures as ye do, and ſet them up in the room of Chriſt; and is there any greater Idolatry in <hi>Rome</hi> than this, to ſay the Bible is the ſword of the Spirit, and the Judge of the Spirit? when it ſaith, <hi>All Judgement is committed to the Sonne, and the Spiritual Man judgeth all things:</hi> And to ſay the Bible is the Guide, Leader, and Rule to walk by, when it ſaith, <hi>That the Sonnes of God were led, and guided by the Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer theſe Queries; was <hi>Abraham, Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> and all the Holy men of God, before <hi>Moſes</hi> time without a a Leader, a Guide, or Judge? or was any of theſe without the Word of the Lord? ſeeing they had not the Bible which which ye ſay is the Rule, and Judge for the Saints to walk by, and the word of the Lord?</p>
            <p>Whether the Jewes that had the Bible, had the Word of the Lord? or heard it at any time? or whether they did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107206:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>not think to have Eternal life in the Scriptures? and ſo make an Idol of that which is profitable in its place as ye do, but were Enemies to the light, as ye are, and would not come to him for life? and whether any by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can come to the knowledge of Chriſt? ſeeing they that had them, as ye have, and were painted with words, and had the ſheeps clothing, but knew not Chriſt thereby? for had they known him, they would not have Crucified the Lord of Life: and by this, and in this, which you call the Law and Teſtimony, they were contending againſt the Law and Teſtimony, as ye are, and ſaid by their law he deſerved to die. And this is the ſtate not onely of you Baptiſts, but of all Sects, and Opinions, and Religions in Chriſtendome, which have ſet up any other thing ſoever, to be Judge, Leader, or Teacher; or call any other thing the Law or Teſtimony, then the Spirit of Propheſie, or the Law, which is Light, <hi>and hath lighted every man that comes into the world.</hi> And the Eye is blinded in you, which ſhould ſee the Body, the life, and ſubſtance, and in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ye are, and in your ſinnes, and in ſorrow ſhall you lie down, and your end ſhall be deſtruction, who are led by any other thing than the light within, in whom are found treaſures of Wiſdome, and treaſures of Knowledge; yea, durable Riches, and exceeding Righteouſneſſe, which exceedeth all yours, which ſpeaketh of Juſtification by Chriſt, but your ſelves in your ſinnes: for there is none comes unto Chriſt, but they come to perfection; neither doth any ſin at all, who abide in him, which is perfect, and cannot ſin; Sin is not of Chriſt, but of the Devil: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee what your way is, that you are in, and what your Ordinances are to you; who are found doing your Fathers work, making it your daily work to ſtrive againſt the Truth, which ſets free from ſin, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did againſt Chriſt, and ſaid they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, and were never in bondage to any: but could not ſee his ſhape, nor hear his Voice, who ſhould have ſet them free from ſin; nor themſelves could they not ſee to be ſervants of ſin, and of their Father the Devil, though they were doing his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107206:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>work, as ye are, for which the Lord God of life, and power, will reward you with Judgement, unleſſe you ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and do no more ſo wickedly.</p>
            <p>And all you profeſſors, of what ſort ſoever, that I may be clear of your bloud, I warn you all in the power of the Lord, do not perſecute thoſe deſpiſed people, which by the Scornes are called Quakers: Do not magnifie your ſelves againſt them, nor give not your power to the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet; nor gather your ſelves with <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> and look not upon them, becauſe the Sun hath looked upon them, and the heat thereof hath ſcorched them, and made them black, for the Lord hath given his Word unto them, and many are they which publiſh it: Kings of Armies ſhall flee apace before the beautiful Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion;</hi> and though they have lain among the pots, yet ſhall they be as the wings of a Dove, covered with ſilver, and her feathers with yellow gold, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13.</p>
            <p>Ye are they which have been as of the off-ſcouring of all things whom my ſoul is joyned unto; and in the bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Life is my ſoul bound up with yours, and in the Book of Life can you ſee my name written with yours? if I forget you, <hi>let my right hand forget her cunning,</hi> and my Tongue fail that it ſpeak no more, ye precious ſons and daughters of <hi>Sion.</hi> Ariſe, and threſh the Mountains, for the Lamb hath opened his mouth, and the threſhing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument is given you, and the two-edged Sword is known. Ariſe, ariſe, and lay your ſwords upon your enemies necks; <hi>Let not your hands ſpare nor your eye pity but wound the wicked, and the hairy ſcalp of them that go on in Rebellion;</hi> and my ſoul ſhall be glad when it ſees the vengeance. Oh my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren! and oh my Siſters, which hath long been rejected and deſpiſed, be ye all faithful to the Lord God Almighty! let Righteouſneſſe and Innocency be the girdle of your loynes, and by you ſhall Kings be ungirded, Judges and Counſellors ſhall be led away ſpoiled; yea, all the Princes, Nobles, and honourable of the earth, by you is the Lord overturning Kingdomes, and eſtabliſhing Kingdomes in Righteouſneſſe, even by you whoſe weapons are not carnal
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107206:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>but mighty, is the Lord God Almighty overturning, and laying the world as a wilderneſs, and deſtroying him that opened not the door of his priſoner, this ſpark is kindled; yea, his holy One will prove a flame, and ſhall burn up the Briers, and Thorns, and the trees of the wilderneſs, and of the forreſt; the Oakes of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and the Cedars of <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> ſhall be few, that a childe may write them: The Lyon is come out of the Thicket, and the deſtroyer of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles hath uttered his voice out of <hi>Sion;</hi> therefore tremble, tremble, and be amazed, ye beaſts of the Field, flee to your ſtrong holds, you whoſe minds be without from the Light, ſee if the Rocks, or your earthly holds, can hide you from the preſence of our God, and of the Lamb; ſee what ye will do in this day wherein the Lord will bear no longer: Ye Prieſts and Magiſtrates, which have long perſecuted this poor, and afflicted people: Repent, repent, and oppreſſe them no longer, for the Lord hath looked upon their low eſtate, yea, he hath remembred his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to a thouſand generations; the Covenant which he made with <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Abraham</hi> his friend, and his ſeed for evermore, even the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which ſerved for a wife, ſhall become thouſands and millions, and poſſeſſe the gates of all that hate them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.60.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> which hath called your ſelves Chriſtians, and have been long faſting, praying, and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a Reformation, and have called your ſelves of Chriſt herein, and have covered your ſelves with the Saints words, and Prophets words, but have been inwardly raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Life and Spirit, and truth which they were in: And I am troubled for you all, and your iniquity lyeth heavy upon me, and what will ye do? and how will you Anſwer before the Lord, that when his Son, which he hath ſent into <hi>England,</hi> to gather his ſheep as a ſhepherd, from all the greedy ſhepherds that hath fed themſelves, and have clothed themſelves, and ſcattered the ſheep of Gods paſture, which are men againſt him have ye all riſen as one man, and ye have reſiſted, and withſtood the Lords Work here in <hi>England,</hi> which is a marvellous work, and a wonder to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107206:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>all who have the profeſſion, but their minds is eſtranged from the light of Chriſt within? And I am troubled at my very heart for you all, for I know your end will be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as wormwood; yea, deſtruction from the Almighty, and a ſtrange puniſhment for all you workers of Iniquity; let your profeſſion be what it will, This is your portion (ſaith the Lord God) unleſſe you repent, and obey the light of Chriſt in you, which is the Lords Candle, and ſearcheth and trieth all your reines, and ſheweth you your hypocriſie, and how you have but diſſembled, and drawn near to the Lord; and with your tongues have cried, Lord, Lord, but your hearts have been far both from him, and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. I ſay, Come down out of all your thoughts, reaſonings, and imaginations, to the light, which is the eye, and ye ſhall ſee the body of ſin is yet ſtanding, and the body of Chriſt have not yet been diſcerned, and ye ſhall ſee the bed whereon ye have ſtretched your ſelves too ſhort; and the covering which ye have had, hath not been of the Spirit, and ſo too narrow to wrap your ſelves in: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I counſel you all, Come to Chriſt, buy of me gold tried in the fire, that ye may be rich; and white rayment, that ye may be clothed, and that your ſhame and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may appear no longer; for Chriſt is come unto you not to bring peace, but war; and againſt you all is it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proclaimed, and your utter deſtruction and ruine is determined of the Lord God of power, unleſſe ye come down to the light in your Conſciences, and take hold of that which is his ſtrength, and ſo make peace, and agree with your adverſary quickly, while he is in the way: He is not come to bring ſalve for you, but a ſword; not to build, but to deſtroy, and pull down the wall you have built, thats daubed with untempered morter: Now is the Sword of the Lord drawn, and made ready for the ſlaughter, and ſhall be bathed in Heaven, and made fat with the bloud of Bulls, Rams, and Goats, even in the blond of all them who are in the ſtubborn fighting, and tearing nature, which have devoured, grieved, and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the innocent lambs, and ſcattered the ſheep of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107206:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſture; now is the axe laid to the trees root, which hath cumbred the ground (read within) Chriſt the light of the world which lighteth every man, and Satan hath been exalted in the temple of God, and in you hath ſhewed and ſate as God, and upon the land of my people is come up thorns and briars, and man which was made upright and perfect, is gone from the light within, in which he was created, and hath ſought ont many inventions, and there hath been ſeeking the Lord in his thoughts, where God was not to be found.</p>
            <p>Come all you Profeſſors, Prieſts and people, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, to the light in you, for there is a way in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, which no other eye can ſee, read <hi>Job</hi> 28.7. if you have an ear to hear, there is a path which no fowl knoweth, and which the Vulters eye hath not ſeen, the Lions whelp hath not trodden it, nor the fierce Lion paſſed by it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35.8. in the habitation of Dragons, an highway ſhall be there, and a way, and it ſhall be called the way of holineſs, <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſhall not paſs over it, but the redeemed of the Lord ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and walk therein,</hi> and the ranſomed of the Lord ſhall come to Sion, with ſongs, and everlaſting joy upon their heads, they ſhall obtain joy, &amp; gladneſs, &amp; ſorrow, and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall flee away, &amp; in this day ſhall be fulfilled that which is written by the Prophet, <hi>With joy ſhall ye draw water out of the wells of Salvation,</hi> Iſai. 12.5. <hi>Sing unto the Lord for he hath done excellent things;</hi> this is known in all the earth, cry out and ſhout thou inhabitant of Sion, for great is the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the midſt of thee, and then ſhall the mountain of the Lords Houſe be eſtabliſhed on the top of all the mountains of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where the ſheep have been ſcattered, even when the Lord hath thorowly purged away your droſs, and taken away all your Tin, and Sion redeemed with judgement, and her converts with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, (mark, your body is the houſe where judgement muſt begin) and the deſtruction of the tranſgreſſors, and ſinners ſhall be together, &amp; they that forſake the Lord ſhall be conſumed; for <hi>they ſhall be as an Oak, whoſe leaf fadeth, and as a garden that hath no water;</hi> read and underſtand,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107206:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Iſai,</hi> the firſt, <hi>The wiſe men with the ear, that can hear, and the ſtrong ſhall be as tow, and the maker of it as a ſpark, and they ſhall both burn together, and none ſhall quench them: And I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning;</hi> Remember <hi>Moſes</hi> the Judge and Counſellor who was faithful in all his houſe; <hi>afterwards thou ſhalt be called the Citie of righteouſneſs, the faithful Citie:</hi> and this is that new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is free, and the Mother of us all, and the Citie, and the way, wherein no unclean thing ſhall enter, but they that have waſhed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. Conſider this all ye that ſpeak of being juſtified by Chriſt, but live at eaſe and pleaſure, and are yet in your ſins, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.13. <hi>And one of the Elders anſwered, ſaying unto me; What are theſe which are arrayed in white robes, and whence came they? And he ſaid to me, theſe are they which came out of great tribulation, and have followed me in the regeneration, and are come from far out of the degeneration, and have waſhed their robes, and made them, white: in the blood of the Lamb; therefore are they before the throne of God, and ſerve him day and night in his Temple</hi> (conſider) <hi>there is no night there, and he that ſitteth on the Throne ſhall dwell among them, they ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more; neither ſhall the Sun light on them, nor any heat</hi> (mark ye hot Profeſſors) <hi>for the Lamb that is in the midt of the Throne ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them unto living fountains of waters, and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes;</hi> and theſe are they which ſing the new ſong, who are paſſed from the old things, from death to life, and ſtand before the Throne of God; and theſe have the new name, even their Fathers Name, and the Name of the City of their God, which name none knows but they that have it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their foreheads; and here is our joy, and our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying is not in the fleſh, nor our boaſting in ſelf, but we glory in God, and our ſouls ſhall make their boaſts in the Lord; this ſhall trouble the prond, but the humble ſhall hear thereof, and be glad: That we know our Redeemer liveth, and our election made ſure unto us, which cannot, be deceived, and our Names written in the Lambs Book of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107206:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>life, before the foundation of the world was laid in mans heart; oh every one that hungreth and thirſteth, eat of the bread which ſatisfies, and feed no longer, nor ſpend your money for that which ſatisfies not; come all to the waters which he hath ſhewed us, as he did to <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 22.1. <hi>A pure river of water of life, clear as chryſtal, proceeding out of the Throne of God, and of the Lamb in the midſt of the ſtreets of it,</hi> come down to the eye, and ſee the River that hath ſtreets, <hi>and of either ſide of the River, was there the tree of life, which bare twelve manner of fruits, and yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her fruit every moneth, and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the Nations.</hi> This is the firſt reſurrection, the firſt, and the laſt, the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and the end; and abides a Prieſt for ever after the Order of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> without beginning of days, or end of life. Conſider this, all ye that are accuſing us for denying the reſurrection, but are yet in your ſins, and have no part in the firſt reſurrection, which we are witneſſes of, for they are bleſſed and holy, that hath part of the firſt reſurrection; for on ſuch the curſe, death and hell hath no power, bleſſed are they that do his Commandments; yea more bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then they that talk of them, for they ſhall have right to this River, and an entrance ſhall be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to this tree of Life, which grows in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God; here are thoſe glorious things wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed and known in them, in whom Chriſt is glorified, which are ſpoken of the City of our glorious God, into which none ſhall enter but ſuch as are purified, and made glorious within; its not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, that ſhall enter in. (Hear O ye Profeſſors) but ſuch as do the will of my Father which is in Heaven, the Kingdome is within, and none but the pure in heart can ſee it, but are crying, Lo here, and lo there, contrary to Chriſts do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which ſaith, Go not out after them, the kingdom is within the ſeed, even the light of the world was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Jews, and was ſown in them, but not grown in them which did crucifie him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. Read and ſee whether your Teachers be not the ſame falſe Teachers,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107206:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>deceivers, and falſe Chriſts, which Chriſt ſaid had the ſheeps clothing, but were inwardly ravened, and did not walk in, but hated the light wherewith he had lighted them, becauſe their deeds were evil.</p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle of <hi>John, John</hi> ſayes, <hi>Little Children, ye have heard ſay, Antichriſt ſhall come in the laſt time; by this we know it is the laſt time, for many Antichriſts are come already:</hi> And in the <hi>Revelations</hi> ye may read, <hi>That the World went out and wondered after the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet, and ſaid, Who is able to make war with the Beaſt, which made war with the Lamb, and ſlew the Saints, and them which kept the teſtimony of Jeſus?</hi> And this is that Myſtery of Iniquity, which began to work in the Apoſtles dayes, even Myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> the great, that had in her hand a golden cup full of Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Abomination, and the Beaſt carried her, which made all Nations, multitudes, tongues and people, Drunk with the wine of her Fornication, and this is 16. hundred years ſince <hi>John</hi> ſaid they were come, which Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, and the world went after them, and they that would not receive the mark of the Beaſt, and fall down to thoſe Laws which he made then, and ever ſince have been looked upon as deceivers, and have been excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, burnt, and tortured, and have not been ſuffered to buy, or ſell, for this many Generations: theſe went out from the true Apoſtles, which preached freely, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no mans ſilver, gold, or apparrel: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>They preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for filthy lucre, their god was their belly, and their end de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and from ſuch turn away, who have a forme, but not the power. Peter</hi> ſayes, <hi>Wo unto them, for they ran greedily after the errour of Balaam,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.14, 15. <hi>And loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe. John,</hi> who preached freely, ſaid, <hi>They went out from them who were in the power, and light of Chriſt.</hi> Mark, they went out from us, who were in the light, which is not of the world: into the world they went, and the world loved them, and heard them, becauſe they were gone from the light, which reproves the deeds of the world, but had the words, and the form, as the true Apoſtles had: theſe the world went, and wondred after; and theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107206:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>were they that was like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> complained of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8, 5. <hi>Having a form of godlineſſe, but denied the power thereof, and life thereof; from ſuch turn away.</hi> And theſe are they that tell you, you cannot be made perfect while you live, and creep into Steeple-houſes, and your old Maſſe-houſes, when they have got an Order from the Beaſt, or received his Mark from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Camebridge;</hi> and there they learn the Letter, Hebrew, Greek, and Latine, and ſet that as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, above Chriſt, and would not come unto him, that they might have life: and ſo they are become Miniſters, and feed people with the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Miniſter that inſtead of Chriſt: And herein they are preaching, and doing like the Miniſters of Chriſt, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres, Pharaohs</hi> Inchanters did, <hi>Exodus</hi> 7.11. So that there is nothing in the true Church, which is in God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but there is the likeneſs in <hi>Babylon,</hi> the falſe Church, and ſynagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; there is preaching, praying, and ſinging among ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, lyars, and drunkards, as there was amongſt the holy Saints, but it is done by another power, and Spirit, as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Inchanters did, who was acted by the dark power of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and not by Chriſt, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was. Now <hi>Moſes</hi> declared, ſaying, <hi>A Prophet like unto me ſhall the Lord God raiſe up in the midſt of your brethren, him ſhall you hear in what ſoever he ſaith unto you.</hi> So all that hearken not to Chriſt, <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.1. which ſaith, <hi>Every one that thiſteth, come ye to the waters; and him that hath no money, come ye buy and eat; yea, come buy wine and milk without money, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out price; wherefore do ye ſpend your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfies not: incline your ears, and come unto me; hear, and your ſouls ſhall live, and I will make an everlaſting covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of</hi> David.</p>
            <p>Conſider this, how long your Miniſters have fed you with the Letter which killeth, inſtead of the Spirit which giveth life: is the Letter the Water here ſpoken of? or is it the bread which ſatisfies? ſeeing you have been feeding ſo long at your Teachers table, and not come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107206:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Truth, which is Chriſt the Bread, and giveth life to the Soul. Conſider, and deal plainly with your ſelves, doth not the Lord ſay, <hi>That all his children ſhall be taught by him, and he will write his law in their hearts, and put his fear in their inward parts.</hi> Jer. 31.31, 33. <hi>And I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people, and they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his brother; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt; and I will forgive their iniquities, and I will remember their ſins no more, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Therefore all turn into the Light, and walk in the light of the Lord, and priſe this day of your Viſitation, before it be hid from your eyes. And from the Lord God this is a warning to you all, that you own that which ſmites you in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; obey it, follow it, and love it, which diſcerneth, and ſheweth you when there is but an evil thought ariſeth in you, as I ſaid before, not to bring peace, but a ſword to convince the World of ſin, and with his ſword to cut down the man of ſin, and to bring to light the hidden things of diſhoneſty; and to ſearch out the hidden things of <hi>Eſau,</hi> whom God hateth; <hi>Eſaus</hi> nature is the ſame as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it was; <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> is yet alive in all the children of Diſobedience, and betrayers of the Lord they are all, which are in their ſins, though they are preaching againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> for killing his brother; <hi>Judas,</hi> for betraying his Lord, as many of this Nations teachers do for money. O <hi>England,</hi> that thou wouldeſt but conſider! leſt this glorious day of Gods everlaſting light and love paſſe over you, and the night come when thou canſt not work; therefore all you prophane ones, that ſeem to be religious, but your tongue is yet at liberty, and unbridled: O what will ye do upon your death beds! Where will ye hide your ſelves, when the Judgement begins in the Temple, and the ſongs of the houſe be turned into howling? what will ye do? and how will ye give an account for every idle word, which ye in your life time have ſpoken for, which ye have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by Gods Witneſſe in your Conſciences, you that live in ſinne, and not in Chriſt, and cannot ceaſe from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107206:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinne; it is becauſe they are gone from the power, even the light of the world, which is the way of righteouſneſſe, in which whoſoever walks, ſtumbles not, nor ſins not, the well is neer come down into the deep: come to the Rock, eat honey, and be ſatisfied, and let your ſouls delight it ſelf in fatneſſe; love not the world, nor the pleaſures, delights, and vanities thereof, but love the light which is not of the world: for if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him, But thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy ſtrength; and this is the ſtrait way, and a gate too narrow for any luſtfull one to walk in; the vain talker is not here, it is a path too narrow for all them which are ſpeaking of Chriſt, the ſtrait way, but themſelves, their tongues, and their hearts at liberty in the fleſh: And O that you would conſider, you that ſpend your dayes in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! will not this prove bondage and bitterneſſe in the latter end! O that you were wiſe to lay it to heart! That you would conſider your latter end, the glorious liberty which is not in the fleſh, nor in the luſts thereof, which the ſervants and Sons of God enjoy, whom you are accuſing, as the worſt of men! did you but poſſeſſe one day, ſurely you would caſt away all your lovers, and ſay, What have I to do any more with Idols? I call you all to partake with me, who are afar off, and ſeparated from the Lord by ſin, as I have ſometime long been, and in that ſtate I was read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtuddying the Scriptures, and the vail being over my heart, I could not ſee them, for they were a parable to me, as now they are to you. But now hath the Lord in his unſearchable loving kindneſſe, which is great towards me, and I cannot utter it, hath revealed his Sonne in me, which makes manifeſt, and reveals the Father: yea, he hath commanded his light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, which was vailed over in my heart, while I was in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and could not comprehend it therein. I ſay it was his love to me, when I was in hatred, and enmity againſt him, following the imaginations of my evil heart; and being in captivity, and bondage, to diverſe hiſts; and ſin
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107206:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>was entred, and death by ſin reigned over the ſeed, to whom all the Promiſes were; the ſeed is Chriſt the Son of God, and the grace of God, and manifeſtation which bringeth ſalvation, &amp; hath appeared to all men; and did all but obey it, &amp; not rebel againſt it, or grieve it, it would be a ſufficient Saviour of it ſelf to every man; and this you muſt all feel working, riſing, and operating in your hearts, and in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and lowlineſs of mind muſt ye receive this ingrafted Word, that ye may grow thereby; and here is the true growth in grace, rather then words or wiſedom; in puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and power, rather then in a painted profeſſion, of which there is enough, and too much in the world, becauſe they are ſayers and not doers, profeſſing Chriſt which they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs not: And oh how ſad is it to hear people ſaying, They hope to be ſaved by Chriſt, and that they are accepted with God in Chriſt Jeſus, and yet this hope doth not purifie them as he is pure, and ſo muſt needs be but as a Spiders web, for ſin is a ſhame for any people, but all who comes to know the true hope, which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory; it makes not aſhamed, for it purifies the heart, and redeems man both out of ſin and ſhame, and what is your faith that leaves you thus in this world, and gives you not victory over it? is not your faith vain, and all vain while Chriſt is not riſen in you? you are in your ſins, and your righteouſneſs, is it any better, if ſo good, as the Scribes and Phariſees which made clean the out-ſide, but inwardly are full of all abomination? therefore come to that, and feel the Lords Talent in you, and hide it no longer in the earth, but improve it to the utmoſt, for that will not be to give an account with joy, but grief; this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is the grace and light of Chriſt which to every man and woman hath appeared, and this is not common grace as your Teachers tell you, but it is the ſaving grace, and would ſave every man, and would not the death of any man, did they but obey it, and not always rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; therefore hear this all yet rebels, even to you I ſpeak, which have long grieved and vexed the good Spirit of the Lord, with whom he is yet ſtriving, be ye never ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107206:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>wicked and vile; though your ſins be as red as ſcarlet, and though you have deeply corrupted your ſelves, and your ſpot is not the ſpot of his children; to you I ſay, in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord, give not ſentence againſt your ſelves, by ſaying, Your wound is incurable, yea though you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed and crucified the innocent in you; do not ſay that your puniſhment is greater then can be born, nor your ſin greater then can be forgiven; for be ye as far off as ever the Prodigal was, or as far off as ever I ſometime was, yet if ye do but ſay in your heart I have ſinned, and it profiteth me not; I will go and return to my Fathers houſe, againſt whom I have ſinned; the father himſelf will come out to meet you, as he did me, even I, who was diſobedient, and afar off, being led away of divers luſts, which ruled in my heart while the God of this world had blinded my eye which ſhould have ſeen my Saviour; and then ſhewed and ſmote me, for in my Conſcience even me hath he gathered off the mountains to himſelf; yea he hath brought me very neer, and reconciled to himſelf by the blood of his Son, that I might make known unto you his everlaſting kindneſs in calling ſinners to repentance while they are in their ſins, and that in the mouth of two or three Witneſſes this Truth may be confirmed to you all. I with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> do ſet to my Seal, and bring in my Teſtimony; read 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.10 to 20. That God deſireth not the deſtruction or the death of him which is deſtroyed, but had rather they would own his light which is Chriſt, his power and ſtrength, and would, and doth give power over all ſin, yea even power to become the Sons of God, which ſin not: And this I declare to you all is not of man, nor mans righteouſneſs, which is as filthy rags; yet it is in man, and there fulfils the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Law now in the Saints as ever he did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>for as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God;</hi> mark the wiſe Profeſſors Prayers, and ſuch as ſay, ye obſerve the Ordinances, and uſe the means, and ſay
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107206:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>you cannot be perfect in this life, but ſay ye are juſtified by Chriſts righteouſneſs which ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us. Conſider this you that would make Chriſt a cover for your ſins, as all doe who know not Chriſt in them the hope of glory. Therefore call not us deceivers any longer, but ſee how Satan is exalted in you, and ye your ſelves are deceived, which are in your ſins and beguiled, and caſt the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt Jeſus (which all that are in, ſin not) and this is true Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for any to be in Chriſt where old things and ſin is done away, for which man is condemned, and unto which the Law was, and is added, and abides in force while men are in their ſins, though in that ſtate which is woful, and for condemnation: You will ſay, you are not under the Law, but under Grace; therefore count not this deceit any longer as you have formerly done, but conſider what have ye to be deceived of, ſeeing ye are in your ſins, and have loſt the elect which cannot be deceived; and the Apoſtles did not write to ſuch as you are, but to the Saints that were in Chriſt Jeſus, and had ſomething more then you have (who are in your ſins) to be deceived of.</p>
            <p>Therefore all come down unto Chriſt the light of the world, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, which is the eye, and ye ſhall ſee all your prayers, righteouſneſſes, Means and Ordinances, which you uſe to get, Chriſt is all one in the ſight of God, with your ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying and drunkenneſs; read <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66. <hi>v.</hi> 2. to 5. Heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en unto this ye proud Profeſſors, but trembles not at the Word of the Lord: <hi>He that killeth an Oxe, as if he ſlew a man; he that ſacrificeth a lamb, as if he cut off a dogs neck; he that offereth an oblation, as if he offered ſwines blood; he that burneth Incenſe, as if he bleſſed an Idol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the ground and reaſon of this, ye that ſay ye cannot be perfect and holy in this life, whether ye are not in your own wayes? and whether ye have not choſen your own wayes? and your ſouls delighted in that which is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto Chriſt, who is the way, the truth, the life;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107206:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and he that is in it ſinneth not, what ever you may ſay, who are in your own inventions, and righteouſneſſe, but are far off from the righteouſneſſe which is near to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the heart, as all are, who ſay <hi>Revelations</hi> are cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for I declare to you all, from my own experience, not from the Letter, but from the Spirit and Power of the Lord, that I never heard the Voice, nor knew the things of God from the Letter, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt: for it hath pleaſed the Father to reveal his Son in me, who is the light, in which light I ſee light, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther revealed, who is the fountain thereof: and broken Ciſterns, and corrupt Fountains are all drinking out of, and feeding upon the wind, and windy doctrine, and vain hopes; and eating that which dieth of it ſelf, and doth not ſatisfie; and are all blind, and dead in their ſins, are all they which ſaith that Revelation are ceaſed.</p>
            <p>And this is a general cry with Prieſts, and Profeſſors, who are gone in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and abides not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, which ſhould reveal the Father, and of all Sects and Opinions whatſoever, they are crying, none can hear the Voice of Chriſt now but in the Letter. To you I ſay, who are ſetting up the Bible to be your Rule, inſtead of the Spirit, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, who thought to have eternal life in the Scriptures, and were painted as ye are with the Saints words, being inwardly ravened from the light and ſpirit of the Lord, which doth reveal, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it did, the things of God. I ſay you are not like to hear his voice, who are gone from the hearing ear; nor to ſee his ſhape, who are gone from the Light, the ſeeing eye; but the Saints and ſheep did then hear his Voice, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him; and I witneſſe his Voice to be heard now, as ever it was, and thouſands in <hi>England</hi> beſides me, though I do confeſſe, you which have the ſheeps clothing, but are not ſheep; do not, nor cannot hear his Voice, no more than the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, who had the ſame clothing, but were inwardly ravened from the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore all that would know. God, or the things of God, muſt come to the meaſure of the Spirit in them; a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107206:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>meaſure of which is given to every man, to profit withall, and this is nigh you in your hearts, and as ye finke downe ye ſhall feele it working, riſing, and operating in you, and as ye are ſtill, ye ſhall feele ye ſpirit of the holy and pure God which hath been impriſoned, and held in captivity under <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the man of ſin, which hath been exalted in you, above the ſpirit of God in you, ſo all in this wait which is underneath the power of darkneſs, and ſhineth in the darkneſs, and out of the darkneſs ſhall it ariſe, for he hath long dwelt in thick darkneſs; and round about him hath been Clouds, &amp; deep Waters: I ſay, wait in patience, all you that ſit in the region, and ſhadow of death, and the light ſhall riſe, until darkneſſe be under his feet, even thoſe dark mountains where you have been ſcattered, and are ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and how beautiful ſhall you witneſſe his feet to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountains? Tongue, nor Pen, cannot utter, even he that publiſheth Salvation, and ſaith unto <hi>Sion,</hi> thy King raignes; and this is the raigne of Chriſt, and the only raign which the Scripture declares of, That all his enemies ſhould be under his feet; for he muſt raign till he have ſubjected all things to himſelf, even all that which hath captivated the Seed in <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe: And then ſhall come to paſſe that ſaying which is written, and nor till then. Here is the patience of the Saints, and here ſhall you feel the ſufferings of Chriſt that are behinde; and here is the time of Tryal, and the very day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> trouble, when he that hath led into captivity, muſt go into captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; even as he aſcends out of the grave, and the pit, he receiveth gifts for men, but man is not meet to partake of the gift, until that nature which would devour, be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, And I ſay, in bowels of everlaſting love, whoſe hearts are but breathing, though never ſo little after the Lord, ſpeak not evil of that you know not, nor judge nothing before the time, until the ſpirit riſe out of priſon in you, unto whom all judgement is committed, and he will judge; even he, who is the judge of all the earth, aright; he will not condemn the righteous, with the wicked, nor ſlay the righteous with the wicked, though man may, who is gone
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107206:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the ſpirit of truth in himſelf, and knows not that there is a lie in his right hand, and ſo calls good, evil, and evil, good; and puts light for darkneſſe (himſelf being in that darkneſs) and darkneſſe for light. I am grieved for the ſons of men at my very heart! and greatly am I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed therewith! and the iniquity of many lieth upon my life; and I am preſſed therewith as a cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaves: And oh! how am I greived to ſee people that call themſelves Chriſtians, and profeſs the ſcripturers to be their rule, how contrary thereunto they walke, and yet are condemning us for denying the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who are in the life of them! And as for your being Chriſtians, there is no ſuch thing, for you do not at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble God, whom you ſay is your Father, nor Chriſt his Son who loveth righteouſneſs, and hates iniquity, and whoſe loins are girt with righteouſneſſe, and whoſe throne is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in holineſs; and the Scepter of his Kingdom, is a right Scepter, and his Kingdom is everlaſting, and in his people; and conſiſt in righteouſneſs, Power, and Glory. And not in talke, and words, which you are in, without the power or Joy in the Holy Ghoſt; and yet you are ſaying, you are his brethren: but to you all I ſay, who are in vaine words, vain thoughts and actions, in pleaſure, frendſhips, and cuſtomes of the world, which fades away as a flower, and withereth as graſs, all repent and turn to the Light, that you may ſee your ſad conditions, and from whence, and from what are you fallen, for he owns you not, ye workers of iniquity; all your Sacrifices, while you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, or regard iniquity in your hearts, are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.3. And ſo to you all, and in love to your ſouls, I ſay, Come down, for your ſtrength is to ſtand ſtill, and to feel a ſeed in your ſelves, though it be but as a grain of muſtard; and as you in patience wait low out of every thought, reaſoning, and imagination, which vails and clouds this pure ſeed which I ſpeak of, you ſhall ſee, or feel it ariſe in you, grow and multiply as the ſtars in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as the ſands in the Sea ſhore without number.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
